# David Soares Batista

## Personal Data

PLACE AND DATE OF BIRTH: Lisboa, January 4th, 1981

PHONE: +351 93 178 31 64 (mobile)

EMAIL: dsbatista@inesc-id.pt

HOMEPAGE: http://davidsbatista.github.io

#### SUMMARY

Experienced in Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning and Information Retrieval. I like to explore and extract knowledge from large datasets, either structured or unstructured.

Currently, I am a researcher at INESC-ID and a Ph.D. candidate at Instituto Superior Técnico, the engineering school from the University of Lisbon. My Ph.D. proposal relates to extracting relationships from textual documents with an on-line classifier based on min-hash and locality sensitive hashing, while generating initial training data for this classifier by a bootstrapping approach relying on distributional word representations (i.e. neural word embeddings).

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

June 2011 - Present

Researcher @ INESC-ID (www.inesc-id.pt)

Within the context of my Ph.D. thesis and research, I developed techniques to analyse large collections of documents:

- Named Entity Recognition and Disambiguation
- Analysis of Network from Entities Co-Occurrences
- Extract Semantic Relationships
- Topic Modelling

SEP. 2008 - May 2011

Researcher @ LASIGE (www.lasige.di.fc.ul.pt)

Developed an information extraction system to generate geographic summaries. Each summary lists geographic entities found in a document and linked (i.e., disambiguated) to a geographic ontology. The system was applied to a crawl of the Portuguese Web using a Hadoop cluster.

## **EDUCATION**

2011 - Sept. 2015 (expected) Doctor of Philos

2007-2009

Doctor of Philosphy (Ph.D.) candidate in Informatics, Instituto Superior Técnico, University Lisbon. Thesis: "Large-Scale Semantic Relationship Extraction"

Master's Degree (M.Sc.) in Information Extraction, Faculty of Sciences. University of Lisbon.

Thesis: "Geographic Text Mining"

2003-2007 Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Informatics Engineering,

Faculty of Sciences, University Lisbon.

2005-2006, Karlsruhe Universität (TH), Germany

Two semesters abroad as an exchange student.

## Professional Experience

Oct. 2007 – Jul. 2008 | Software Developer @ Nokia Siemens Networks

Responsible for different modules within a mobile network monitoring system. Tasks included the implementation of new features and

code maintenance.

Technologies: Java, CORBA, Oracle

Nov. 2004 - Jul. 2005

IT support @ Informatics Centre, University of Lisbon

- Linux network administration
- Troubleshooting network problems
- Technical support regarding software and hardware problems

Nov. 2003 - Mar. 2004

Sysadmin @ Faculty of Sciences, University of Lisbon

- Administration of a mixed Linux/Windows environment
- Maintenance of services: HTTP, SMTP/IMAP, DNS, LDAP, IPTables

## LANGUAGES

Portuguese: Native Speaker

English: Spoken: Fluent Written: Fluent

GERMAN: Spoken: Good Written: Fair Certification: Goethe-Zertifikat B.1

## Computer Skills

Programming Languages: Java, Python, Unix Shell Scripting

Databases/NoSQL: MySQL, PostgreSQL, REDIS

Full-Text Index/Retrieval: Apache Lucene/Solr

Machine Learning Libraries: Python Scikit-Learn, Gensim, SVM<sup>light</sup>
Natural Language Processing Libraries: Python NLTK, Stanford CoreNLP, LingPipe

Distributed Computing: Apache Hadoop

## SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Semi-Supervised Bootstrapping of Relationship Extractors with Distributional Semantics. David S Batista, Bruno Martins, and Mário J Silva. In *Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing-EMNLP'15*. ACL, 2015. (Honorable Mention for Best Short Paper)

A Minwise Hashing Method for Addressing Relationship Extraction from Text. David S Batista, Rui Silva, Bruno Martins, and Mário J Silva. In Web Information Systems Engineering-WISE'13. Springer, 2013.

Exploring DBpedia and Wikipedia for Portuguese Semantic Relationship Extraction David Soares Batista, David Forte, Rui Silva, Bruno Martins, and Mário J. Silva. *Linguamática*, 5(1), 2013. Linguamática, 2013

Toponym Disambiguation using Ontology-based Semantic Similarity David S Batista, João D Ferreira, Francisco M Couto, and Mário J Silva. In *Computational Processing of the Portuguese Language 2012*. Springer, 2012

A Statistical Study of the WPT05 Crawl of the Portuguese Web David Batista and Mário J. Silva. In *In FALA 2010 VI Jornadas en Tecnología del Habla and II Iberian SLTech Workshop* Universidade de Vigo, 2010.

Geographic Signatures for Semantic Retrieval David S Batista, Mário J Silva, Francisco M Couto, and Bibek Behera. In *Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Geographic Information Retrieval* ACM, 2010.